Michael Hausenblas

Date Of Birth 1975-07-03

Nationality Austria

Residency 32 Bushypark Lawn, Galway, Ireland

Web http://mhausenblas.info/

Email <u>michael.hausenblas@gmail.com</u>



Michael helps appops to build and operate modern applications in a scalable manner. He has a background in large-scale data integration, the Hadoop/NoSQL ecosystem, as well as containerized workloads. Contributing to open source software (incl. DC/OS, Kubernetes, Apache Mesos, Marathon, Apache Drill, Apache Spark), Michael shares his experiences with distributed systems through public speaking engagements (Velocity, Strata, Software Circus, OSCON, Devoxx, LinuxCon) as well as via books, articles, webinars, blog posts and interviews.

He has been active as a developer advocate at Mesosphere Inc. (world-wide) and MapR Technologies (EMEA) since 2013 where he supported the Sales and Marketing teams and took care of partners, resulting in multi-million Euro business deals. Prior to that, Michael was a Research Fellow at the National University of Ireland, Galway where he acquired research funding totalling over €4M, working with multinational corporations such as Fujitsu, Samsung and Microsoft as well as governmental agencies in Ireland.

Positions

05/2015 – ongoing	Developer and Cloud Advocate at Mesosphere Inc.
01/2013 - 04/2015	Chief Data Engineer at MapR Technologies
11/2010 - 12/2012	Research Fellow, Head of Linked Data Research Centre, NUIG
11/2008 – 11/2010	Postdoctoral researcher at the Digital Enterprise Research Institute, National University of Ireland, Galway (NUIG)
09/2001 – 11/2008	Researcher and developer (Semantic Web, multimedia metadata) at JOANNEUM RESEARCH GmbH

Professional Activities

2013 — ongoing	 Public speaking engagements (Velocity, Strata, OSCON, Devoxx, LinuxCon, various Mesos, Docker, Kubernetes user groups) Maintaining advocacy sites (label-schema.org, p24e.io, spark-stack.org) and giving Mesos/Kubernetes/Spark training Designing data-intensive applications, both on-premise and cloud-based; EMEA-wide pre-sales experience for a Big Data platform Mentoring (IoT) start-ups and technical partner management Writing books/articles (O'Reilly), webinars (DC/OS, data pipelines, etc.), and interviews (technical/strategic)
2006 – 2012	 Working Group co-chair at World Wide Web Consortium Published community standards (incl. RFC7111) at IETF
2001 – 2012	 Contributed to seven international research projects and served as the project co-ordinator of a two-year Support Action Published over 50 papers and served on 60+ Programme and Organisation Committees at various international conferences and workshops as well as journals

Education and University Studies

09/2008	PhD viva voce. Doctor technicae (Dr. techn.) from TUG, Austria
2004 – 2008	Doctoral studies at TUG, Austria
04/2004	Final diploma examination; Master of Science (MSc.) from TUG
1995 – 2004	University studies of Telematics at Graz University of Technology (TUG), Austria

Competencies

Languages	Primary: Shell scripts, Go, Python
	Secondary: JavaScript, Scala, Java

For code samples see also: https://github.com/mhausenblas/

Tooling	 Containers (cgroups/namespaces, Docker, Apache Mesos/ Marathon, Kubernetes, DC/OS, registries)
	 Hadoop core (HDFS, MapReduce) and ecosystem components
	such as Spark, HBase, Hive, Drill, etc.
	 laaS-level public cloud computing (AWS, Azure, Google Cloud)

• High social competence

• Visionary and creative

• Intercultural alignment

Soft Skills

Good portion of humour